Guide to the Chinese Land Records, 1584-1978 EAL.2011.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chinese Land Records
1584-1978
ULS Archives & Special Collections
EAL.2011.01
240 items (5 boxes)
These Chinese Land Records are important and valuable primary documentation that reflect the land ownership in different historical periods, land tenure changes and land management system of China. As historical records they are indispensable for research and studies of Chinese politics, economy, social life, etc. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online. 这些珍贵的原始文献不仅提供了中国不同历史时期的土地所有，产权转让，土地管理系统的历史信息，也是研究中国政治史，经济史，社会生活史不可或缺的珍贵史料。检索指南包含了数字化副本​。
Access Restrictions
No restrictions. 无限制。
Acquisition Information
From Fujian, China in June 2011. 2011年6月购于中国福建。
Arrangement
The land records are in chronological order. 所收文件依时间顺序排列。
History
After years tracing on internet in Feb. 2011 Haihui Zhang, Chinese Studies Librarian, got a phone contact with a private collector from Fujian Province, China who has collected Chinese land deeds. Upon Haihui's request the collector agreed to hold his land deed collection for ULS' consideration. In March, Dr. Hong Xu, the Head of EAL had a trip to Taiwan and stop by the collector's home in Fuzhou, Fujian Province. Hong took photos back. In June, Hong Xu and Haihui Zhang went to Shanghai for a conference titled "Chinese Studies in North America" and then took a trip to Fuzhou. They spend two days at the collector's home and purchased land deeds collected by the collector as a package. Then, a vendor from Beijing contacted the collector helped processing this purchase for ULS. 经过多年努力，中国研究馆员张海惠在2010年与一位私人收藏家取得了电话联系，了解其收藏情况，尤其是土地文书类原始文献。 2011年3月，匹兹堡大学东亚图书馆前馆长徐鸿赴台湾开会，之后短暂停留福州，并带回照片数枚。6月，徐鸿和张海惠参加在上海举行的"北美中国学研究国际学术讨论会"，会后再次前往福州并为匹兹堡大学图书馆购买了这批中国土地文书文献，以供学者研究之需。
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available online. 检索指南中包含了在线数字化副本。
Scope and Content Notes
The collection of Chinese Land Records at University Library System, University of Pittsburgh include land deeds, property trade documents, possession draw documents, tax bills, etc. It includes 220 pieces that span over three hundred years from the Ming Dynasty (1368-1644) to mid-twentieth century. The majority of them are from Fujian Province and several are from other provinces. 匹兹堡大学图书馆拥有的中国土地文书文献共220份，包括地契、土地买卖文书、家族析产书、土地税收据，等等。时间跨度上自明代(1368-1644)，下至20世纪50年代。除少部分出自其他省份，绝大部分出自于福建省。
For each item the document type is indicated as "Government" or "Personal." "Government" refers to a document with a seal of local government and "Personal" refers to ones without a government seal. 每条记录含有文件类别(Government 或 Personal). 在此，Government和Personal仅用于区分某文件是否有地方政府官印。
Most of this collection contains Chinese land records. However, there are a few of documents that do not belong to this category, such as tax certificates, tax stamps, trademarks, working transfer orders, etc. Since they were purchased as a whole, they were included in this collection as well. 此数据库的绝大部分文件为土地文书，极少数则不属土地文书范畴，如纳税证明，税票，商标，介绍信等。因这些文献与土地文书打包整体购进，故亦包括在此数据库中。
Some of the records have more than one image so be sure to scroll down to see all. 绝大部分记录含一幅图像，少数含两幅以上。若发现描述文字与图像内容有所出入，请向下移动鼠标以确定看到全部图像。
Accruals
An addition to the collection arrived in late 2015. These are indicated in the finding aid by alphabetical letters in the File Folder such as 33A. These 20 folders can be physically found in Box 5.
Real property, Exchange of -- China -- Fujian Sheng; Land titles -- China; Land titles -- China -- Fujian Sheng; Deeds -- China; Deeds -- China -- Fujian Sheng; Fujian Sheng (China); Real property, Exchange of -- China
- Owner: 張炳財 [ZHANG Bingcai] -- Place: 福建省連城縣 [Fujian Sheng Liancheng Xian] -- Personal, 明萬曆12年 [1584] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Seller: 范南山 [FAN Nanshan] -- Personal, 清順治16年 [1659] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Seller: 徐正耀 [XU Zhengyao] -- Place: unknown -- Government, 清康熙17年 [1678] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Owner: 黃毓扆 [HUANG Yuyi] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆25年, 清乾隆32年 [1760, 1767] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Seller: 許瓊栢 [XU Qiongbai] -- Buyer: 吳省忠 [WU Shengzhong] -- Place: 福建省永定縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongding Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆26年, 清乾隆27年 [1761, 1762] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Seller: 徐幹通 [XU Gantong] -- Buyer: 熊孫? [XIONG Sun?] -- Place: 福建省南平縣 [Fujian Sheng Nanping Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆32年 [1767] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Seller: 李有定 [LI Youding] -- Buyer: 謝氏 [XIE] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆44年 [1779] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Owner: 黃鴻吉 [HUANG Hongji] --Seller: 熊長生 [XIONG Changsheng] -- Buyer: 熊亨讀 [XIONG Hengdu] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆49年, 清道光10年 [1784, 1830] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Seller: 應梓龍 [YING Zilong] -- Buyer: 劉繼伍 [LIU Jiwu] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清乾隆47年 [1782] (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Seller: 可翅 [KE Chi] -- Place: unknown --Personal, 清乾隆47年 [1782] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Seller: 劉盛章 [LIU Shengzhang] --Buyer: 劉咸安 [LIU Xian'an] and 劉道建 [LIU Daojian] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶3年 [1798] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Seller: 邱有本 [QIU Youben], 邱有炳 [QIU Youbing] and 邱傳學 [QIU Chuanxue] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Personal, 清嘉慶7年 [1802] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Owner: 劉咸安 [LIU Xian'an] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶10年 [1805] (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Seller: 趙守藻 [ZHAO Shouzao] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶10年 [1805] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Seller: 黃隆貫 [HUANG Longguan] -- Buyer: 陳國遠代陳國龍 [CHEN Huoyuan represents CHEN Guolong] -- Personal, 清嘉慶10年, 清嘉慶12年, 清嘉慶13年 [1805, 1807, 1808] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Owner: 吳秉鑒 [WU Bingjian] -- Seller: 吳秉鑒 [WU Bingjian] -- Buyer: 謝先經 [XIE Xianjing] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶10年, 清嘉慶21年 [1805, 1816] (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Owner: 羅? [LUO ?] -- Place: 安徽省歙縣 [Anhui Sheng She Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶12年 [1807] (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Seller: 劉欽達(違) [LIU Qinda(wei)] -- Buyer: 劉王建 [LIU Wangjian] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] --Government, 清嘉慶18年 [1813] (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Seller: 趙守藻 [ZHAO Shouzao] -- Buyer: 林有柱 [LIN Youzhu] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清嘉慶22年 [1817] (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Seller: 王志撥？ [WANG Zhibo] -- Buyer: 陳 [CHEN] -- Personal, 清道光2年 [1822] (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Seller: 陳國遠（立票人） [CHENG Guoyuan] -- Buyer: 葉宜全（保票人） [YE Yiquan] -- Personal, 清道光2年 [1829] (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Seller: 陳國遠（立票人） [CHENG Guoyuan] -- Buyer: 葉宜全（保票人） [YE Yiquan] -- Personal, 清道光9年 [1829] (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Seller: 黃隆貫 [HUANG Longguan] -- Buyer: 陳國遠 [CHEN Guoyuan] -- Place:unknown -- Personal, 清道光9年 [1829] (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Folders 24-1 thru 24-7 contain the identical document; therefore it was only scanned once. 文件夹24-1至24-7包含相同的文档，因此仅做一次扫描归档。
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-2)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-3)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-4)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-5)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-6)
- Owner: 義容 [Yirong] -- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清道光17年 [1837] (Box 1, Folder 24-7)
- Seller: 葉國佑 [YE Guoyou] -- Buyer: 紳 [SHEN] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清道光19年 [1839] (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Owner: 林氏 [LIN Shi] -- Personal, 清道光27？年 [1840] (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Owner: 陳行典 [CHENG Xingdian] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Personal, 清道光20年 [1840] (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Seller: 劉孝良 [LIU Xiaoliang] -- Buyer: 林高滿 [LIN Gaoman] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 清道光20年, 民國26年 [1840, 1937] (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Seller: 林忠 [LIN Zhong] and 林榮[LIN Rong]-- Buyer: 賴榮松 [LAI Rongsong] -- Place: Unknown -- Personal, 清道光21年 [1841] (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Seller: 黃維裕 [HUANG Weiyu] and 黃維岑[HUANG Weicen] -- Personal, 清道光22年 [1842] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Seller: 林厚成 [LIN Houcheng] and 林厚祿 [Lin Houlu] and 林厚祥 [Lin Houxiang] -- Buyer: 葉成 [YE Cheng] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Personal, 清道光24年, 清道光25年 [1844, 1845] (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Owner: 林元鼎 [LIN Yuanding] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清道光29年 [1849] (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Seller: 林世奕 [LIN Shiyi] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Personal, 清道光30年 [1850] (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Seller: 游振梅 [pin yin] -- Buyer: 楊坤貞 [pin yin] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Personal, 道光30年, 同治9年, ，民国12年 [1850, 1870, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 33A)
- Owner: 葉成 [YE Cheng] --Seller: 林厚成 [LIN Houcheng] -- Buyer: 葉成 [YE Cheng] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣和侯官縣[Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian and Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清咸豐4年, 民國2年[1854, 1913] (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Seller: 陳士曾 [CHEN Shizeng] -- Place: unknown -- Government, 清咸豐8年 [1858] (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Seller: 张华富 [ZHANG Huafu] -- Personal, 清同治元年 [1862] (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Seller: 楊兆通 [YANG Zhaotong] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Personal, 清同治元年 [1862] (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Seller: 黃志林 [HUANG Zhilin] -- Buyer: 劉子珜 [LIU Ziyang] -- Personal, 清同治2年 [1863] (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Owner: 張利禧 [ZHANG Lixi] --Seller: 鄭嬌姑 [ZHENG Jiaogu] -- Buyer: 鄭淳氏 [ZHENGchunshi] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清同治3年, 清同治11年 [1864, 1872] (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Seller: 吳開揚 [WU Kaiyang] -- Buyer: 陳世旺 [CHEN Shiwang] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 同治3年 [1864] (Box 1, Folder 39A)
- Seller: 德詮（僧人） [Dequan] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清同治4年 [1866] (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Seller: 林春源 [LIN Chunyuan] -- Place: 福建省閩邑 [Fujian Sheng Min Yi] -- Personal, 清同治5年 [1866] (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Seller: 楊鵬超（出租） [YANG Pengchao] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清同治5年, 清同治10年 [1866, 1871] (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Owner: 劉景茂 [LIU Jingmao] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清同治6年 [1867] (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Seller: 林邦端 [LIN Bangduan] -- Buyer: 程利欲 [Cheng Liyu] and 程利霖[Cheng Lilin] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清同治7年, 清同治12年, 民國5年 [1868, 1873, 1916] (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Seller: 黃奶壽 [HUANG Naishou] -- Personal, 清同治8年 [1869] (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Seller: ?輝煌 [? Huihuang] -- Buyer: 蘇坐標 [SU Zuobiao] -- Place: 福建省屏南縣 [Fujian Sheng Pingnan Xian] -- Government, 清同治8年 [1869] (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Owner: 阮承苑 [RUAN Chengyuan] --Seller: 黃象智 [HUANG Xiangzhi] and 劉貞文[LIU Zhenwen] -- Buyer: 劉貞文 [ LIU Zhenwen] and 陸元盛 [LU Yuansheng]-- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清同治8年, 清光緒18年, 清光緒25年 [1869, 1892, 1899] (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Owner: 王元靄 [WANG Yuanai] --Seller: 林春源 [LIN Chunyuan] -- Buyer: 王元靄 [WANG Yuanai] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清同治8年, 民國2年, 民國17年 [1869, 1913, 1928] (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Owner: 張蘭芬 [ZHANG Lanfen] --Seller: 張昌暢 [ZHANG Changchang] -- Buyer: （張）邦昔 [(ZHANG) Bangxi] -- Place: 福建省屏南縣和古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Pingnan Xian and Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清同治9年, 清光緒33年 [1870, 1907] (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Seller: 方元慈 [FANG Yuanci] -- Buyer: 方潮濤 [FANG Chaotao] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清同治10年, 民國2年 [1871, 1913] (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Seller: 程姑仔 [CHENG Guzai] -- Buyer: 金寶 [JIN Bao] -- Personal, 清同治9年 [1870] (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Seller: 陳裔煌 [CHEN Yihuang] -- Buyer: 鄭璟 [ZHENG Jing] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 同治11年 [1872] (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Seller: 吳開成 [WU Kaicheng] -- Buyer: 陳 [CHEN] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清同治12年 [1873] (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Seller: 林應香 [LIN Yingxiang] -- Buyer: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒元年 [1875] (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Seller: 祿中 [Luzhong] -- Place: 福建省永安縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒2年 [1876] (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Seller: 康宗瑞 [KANG Zongrui] -- Buyer: 陳連孫 [CHEN Liansun] -- Personal, 清光緒5年 [1879] (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Seller: 林春發 [LIN Chunfa] -- Buyer: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒7年 [1881] (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Seller: 林秋溥 [LIN Qiupu] -- Buyer: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒10年 [1884] (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Seller: 林萬利 [LIN Wanli] -- Buyer: 官方政府 [Goverment] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒10年 [1884] (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Owner: 高恭地[GAO Gongdi] -- Place: 福建省福清縣[Fujian Sheng Fuqing Xian] -- Goverment, 清光緒12年 [1886] (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Owner: 林萬利 [LIN Wanli] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒12年 [1886] (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Seller: 王師禮 [WANG Shili] -- Buyer: 許大華 [XU Dahua] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒12年, 民國2年 [1886, 1913] (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Seller: 王錦發 [WANG Jinfa] -- Buyer: 王錦枝 [WANG Jinzhi] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian ] -- Personal, 清光緒13年 [1887] (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Seller: 陳必清 [CHEN Biqing] -- Buyer: 陳必泉 [CHEN Biquan] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清光緒13年 [1887] (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Place: unknown -- Personal, 清光緒13年 [1887] (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Seller: 陸元規 [LU Yuangui] -- Buyer: 陸元賜 [LU Yuanci] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 清光緒14年, 民國2年 [1888, 1913] (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Seller: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Buyer: 林秋溥 [LIN Qiupu] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒13年 [1888] (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Seller: 陳必清 [CHEN Biqing] -- Buyer: 陳必泉 [CHEN Biquan] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清光緒14年 [1888] (Box 2, Folder 68)
- Seller: 陳必清 [CHEN Biqing] -- Buyer: 陳必泉 [CHEN Biquan] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清光緒14年 [1888] (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Seller: 黃振發 [HUANG Zhenfa] -- Buyer: 高 [GAO] -- Place: 福建省閩邑 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Personal, 清光緒15年 [1889] (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Seller:高金亮 [GAO Jinliang] --Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Personal, 光绪15年, 光绪16年 [1889, 1890] (Box 2, Folder 70A)
- Seller: 張銓銓 [ZHANG Quanquan] -- Buyer: 鄒道明 [ZOU Daoming] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Personal, 光绪15年, 光绪23年 [1889, 1897] (Box 2, Folder 70B)
- Seller: 吳開成 [WU Kaicheng] -- Buyer: 陳氏 [Chenshi] -- Place: 福建省閩邑（縣） [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清同治9年 [1890] (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Seller: 藍炳孫 [LAN Bingsun] -- Buyer: 程長孫 [CHENG Changsun] -- Personal, 清光緒16年 [1890] (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Owner: 陳雅 [CHEN Ya], 陳道書 [CHEN Daoshu], 陳建璽 [CHEN Jianxi] and 陳成嘉[CHEN Chengjia]-- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清光緒16年, 清光緒18年 [1890, 1892] (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Owner: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Personal, 清光緒17年 [1891] (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Owner: 陳亮 [CHEN Liang] and 李清 [LI Qing] -- Place: 福建省 [Fujian Sheng] -- Government, 清光緒18年, 清光緒19年, 清光緒20年 [1892, 1893, 1894] (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Seller: 王兆熙（出租） [WANG Zhaoxi] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒19年 [1893] (Box 2, Folder 76)
- Seller: 王兆熙 [WANG Zhaoxi] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒20年 [1894] (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Seller: 王兆熙 [WANG Zhaoxi] -- Buyer: 林 [LIN] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒20年 [1894] (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Owner: 鄭其英 [ZHENG Qiying] and 沈齊 [SHEN Qi] -- Place: 福建省永安县和永福县 [Fujian Sheng Yongan Xian and Yongfu Xian] -- Government, 清光緒21年, 清光緒26年 [1895, 1900] (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Seller: 蘇章林 [SU Zhanglin] -- Buyer: 劉仕懋 [LIU Shimao] -- Personal, 清光緒24年 [1898] (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Seller: 張寶詨 [ZHANG Baoxiao] -- Buyer: 程長孫 [CHENG Changsun] -- Personal, 清光緒25年 [1890] (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Seller: 鄒允春 [ZOU Yunchun] -- Buyer: 和意軒老人會 [Heyixuan Laorenhui] -- Place: 福建省閩邑（縣） [Fujian Sheng Min Xian ] -- Government, 清光緒26年 [1900] (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Owner: 沈齊 [SHEN Qi] -- Place: 福建省永安縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongan Xian] -- Government, 清光緒26年 [1900] (Box 2, Folder 83)
- Seller: 鄒允春 [ZOU Yunchun] -- Buyer: 秋意軒老人會 [Qiuyixuan Laoren Hui] -- Place: N/A -- Personal, 光绪26年 [1900] (Box 2, Folder 83A)
- Seller: 林與清 [LIN Yuqing] -- Place: unknown --Personal, 清光緒29年 [1903] (Box 2, Folder 84)
- Owner: 金寬英 [JIN Kuanying] -- Seller: 張文楚 [ZHANG Wenchu] -- Buyer: 金寬英 [JIN Kuanying] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 清光緒29年, 民囯32年 [1903, 1943] (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Owner: 黃財業 [HUANG Caiye] -- Seller: 許春願 [XU Chunyuan] -- Buyer: 黃財業 [HUANG Caiye] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 清光緒30年, 民國32年 [1904, 1943] (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Seller: 林為良 [LIN Weiliang] -- Buyer: 林可瓊 [LIN Keqiong] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清光緒32年 [1906] (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Seller: 郭宗仲 [GUO Zongzhong] -- Buyer: 王齊發 [WANG Qifa] -- Personal, 清光緒32年 [1906] (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Seller: 郭成亮 [GUO Chengliang] -- Buyer: 王駿發 [WANG Junfa] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Personal, 光绪32年, 民国3年, 民国十八年, 1955 [1906, 1914, 1929, 1955] (Box 2, Folder 88A)
- Seller: 郭宗仲 [GUO Zongzhong] -- Buyer: 王齊發 [WANG Qifa] -- Place: 福建閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Personal, 光绪32年, 民国10年 [1906, 1921] (Box 2, Folder 88B)
- Seller: 何金盛 [HE Jinsheng] -- Buyer: 何振華 [HE Zhenhua] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清宣統元年 [1909] (Box 2, Folder 89)
- Seller: 熾原 [Chiyuan] -- Buyer: 尚堃 [Shangkun] -- Place: unknown -- Government, 清宣統元年 [1909] (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Seller: 開保 [Kaibao] -- Government, 清宣統2年 [1910] (Box 2, Folder 91)
- Seller: 劉嘉命 [LIU Jiaming] -- Buyer: 劉源森 [LIU Yuansen] -- Place: 福建省建陽縣 [Fujian Sheng Jianyang Xian] -- Government, 清宣統2年 [1910] (Box 2, Folder 92)
- Seller: 王昌年 [WANG Changnian] -- Buyer: 李學堃 [LI Xuekun] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 清宣統2年, 民國4年 [1910, 1915] (Box 2, Folder 93)
- Seller: 方兆揚 [FANG Zhaoyang] -- Buyer: 方亨猷 [FANG Hengyou] -- Place: 福建閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Personal, 清宣统2年, 民国4年 [1910, 1915] (Box 2, Folder 93A)
- Seller: 林可瓊 [LIN Keqiong] -- Buyer: 劉興國 [LIU Xingguo] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 94)
- Seller: 王聯鄧 [WANG Liandeng] -- Buyer: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 95)
- Owner: 林有柱 [LIN youzhu] -- Buyer: 趙守藻 [ZHAO Shouzao] -- Place: 福建省侯官縣 [Fujian Sheng Houguan Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 96)
- Seller: 林應香 [LIN Yingxiang] -- Buyer: 林萬開 [LIN Wankai] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 97)
- Seller: 余德光 [YU Deguang] -- Buyer: 林聖魁 [LIN Shengkui] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 98)
- Owner: 陳必泉 [CHEN Biquan] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 99)
- Owner: 張傳珍 [ZHANG Chuanzhen] -- Place: 福建省屏南縣 [Fujian Sheng Pingnan Xian] -- Government, 民國2年 [1913] (Box 2, Folder 100)
- Owner: 陳琮細 [CHEN Congxi] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民国2年, 民国十七年 [1913, 1928] (Box 2, Folder 100A)
- Seller: 林宜新 [LIN Yixin] -- Buyer: 林久樹 [LIN Jiushu] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國4年 [1915] (Box 2, Folder 101)
- Owner: 陳朝朋 [CHEN Chaopeng] -- Place: 福建省連江縣 [Fujian Sheng lianjiang Xian] -- Government, 民國4年 [1915] (Box 2, Folder 102)
- Owner: 雷汝知 [LEI Ruzhi] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 民國4年 [1915] (Box 2, Folder 103)
- Seller: 長忠 [Changzhong] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 洪憲元年 [1916] (Box 2, Folder 104)
- Seller: 維衜 [Weidao] -- Personal, 民國丁巳6年 [1917] (Box 2, Folder 105)
- Seller: 陳燦祥 [CHEN Canxiang] -- Buyer: 吳右嚴？ [WU Youyan?] -- Place: 福建省閩邑 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 民國6年 [1917] (Box 2, Folder 106)
- Owner: 黃遠容 [HUANG Yuanrong], 黃同華 [HUANG,Tonghua], 黃同德 [HUANG Tongde], 黃國興[HUANG Guoxing] and 黃國義[HUANG Guoyi] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國6-15年 [1917-1926] (Box 2, Folder 107)
- Seller: 陳燦祥 [CHEN Canxiang] -- Buyer: 吳 [WU] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian ] -- Government, 民國7年 [1918] (Box 2, Folder 108)
- Seller: 陳吳氏 [CHEN Wushi] -- Buyer: 吳右岩 [WU Youyan] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Personal, 民国7年, 民国12年, 民国21年 [1918, 1923, 1932] (Box 2, Folder 108A)
- Seller: 張氏 [ZHANG] -- Buyer: 林欽祥 [LIN Qinxiang] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國9年 [1920] (Box 2, Folder 109)
- Owner: 黃雲村? [HUANG Yuncun] and 黃汝勷 [HUANG Rurang] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國9-14年 [1920-1925] (Box 2, Folder 110)
- Owner: 林仁典等 [LIN Rendian] etc. -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國9-15年 [1920-1926] (Box 3, Folder 111)
- Owner: 黃同華 [HUANG Tonghua] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國9-15年 [1920-1926] (Box 3, Folder 112)
- Owner: 陳明 [CHEN Ming] -- Place: 福建省閩縣 [Fujian Sheng Min Xian] -- Government, 民國9-21年 [1920-1932] (Box 3, Folder 113)
- Seller: 林祥德 [LIN Xiangde] -- Buyer: 張經炎 [ZHANG Jingyan] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國10年 [1921] (Box 3, Folder 114)
- Owner: 謝祀初 [XIE Qichu] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 民國10年 [1921] (Box 3, Folder 115)
- Seller: 姚望兌 [YAO Wangdui] and 姚望駀 [YAO Wangyou] -- Government, 民國10年 [1921] (Box 3, Folder 116)
- Owner: 黃汝勷 [HUANG Rurang] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國11年 [1922] (Box 3, Folder 117)
- Owner: 黃乞容等 [HUANG Qirong] etc. -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國12-19年 [1923-1930] (Box 3, Folder 118)
- Seller: 聖余 [SHENG Yu] -- Buyer: 西房眾 [Xi Fang Zhong] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Personal, 民国12年, 民国19年 [1923, 1930] (Box 3, Folder 118A)
- Seller: 王三妹 [WANG Sanmei] -- Buyer: 陳軍漢 [CHEN Junhan] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國13年 [1924] (Box 3, Folder 119)
- Seller: 王三妹 [WANG Sanmei] -- Buyer: 陳軍漢 [CHEN Junhan] -- Place: 福建聲閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民国13年, 民国17年 [1924, 1928] (Box 3, Folder 119A)
- Seller: 林久興 [LIN Jiuxing], 林可鑒 [LIN Kejian] and 林久澍 [LIN Jiushu]-- Personal, 民國13年 [1924] (Box 3, Folder 120)
- Seller: 陳敬侯 [CHEN Jinghou] -- Buyer: 子秀 [ZI Xiu] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 民國13年 [1924] (Box 3, Folder 121)
- Owner: 黃同德 [HUANG Tongde] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國13, 15年 [1924, 1926] (Box 3, Folder 122)
- Seller: 張銓銓 [ZHANG Quanquan] -- Buyer: 鄒道明 [ZOU Daoming] -- Place: 福建省閩侯縣 [Fujian Sheng Minhou Xian] -- Government, 民國14年 [1925] (Box 3, Folder 123)
- Seller: 林履同 [LIN Lutong] -- Buyer: 張炳源 [ZHANG Bingyuan] -- Place: 福建省古田縣 [Fujian Sheng Gutian Xian] -- Government, 民國14年 [1925] (Box 3, Folder 124)
- Seller: 金輯和 [JIN Jihe] -- Buyer: 金信江 [JIN Xinjiang] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國14年, 民國32年 [1925, 1943] (Box 3, Folder 125)
- Seller: 朝官 [Chaoguan] -- Buyer: 文鳳 [Wenfeng] -- Place: 福建省 [Fujian Sheng] -- Government, 民國15年 [1926] (Box 3, Folder 126)
- Owner: 黃同華 [HUANG Tonghua] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國15年 [1926] (Box 3, Folder 127)
- Owner: 黃國興等 [HUANG Guoxing] etc. -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民國15-16年 [1926-1927] (Box 3, Folder 128)
- Owner: 賴國才 [LAI Guocai] -- Place: 福建省 [Fujian Sheng] -- Government, 民國16年 [1927] (Box 3, Folder 129)
- Seller: 黃丁荃 [HUANG Dingquan] -- Buyer: 黃花?蘭(租客) [HUANG Hua?lan] -- Personal, 民國16年 [1927] (Box 3, Folder 130)
- Seller: 文鳳 [WEN Feng] -- Place: 福建省閩清縣 [Fujian Sheng Minqing Xian] -- Government, 民國16年, 民國17年 [1927, 1928] (Box 3, Folder 131)
- Seller: 陳兆濤 [CHEN Zhaotao] -- Buyer: 陳兆和 [CHEN Zhaohe] -- Place: 福建省永泰縣 [Fujian Sheng Yongtai Xian] -- Government, 民国16年 [1927] (Box 3, Folder 131A)